Finding Aid for the Alexander Kolin Papers LSC.0966
UCLA Library Special Collections
Alexander Kolin papers
1929-1990
UCLA Library Special Collections
Kolin, Alexander
LSC.0966
1.6 Linear Feet (3 boxes and 1 flat box)
The collection consists of correspondence (including letters from Albert Einstein), United States patents for Kolin's inventions, and awards.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Peter S. Willcox, 2005.
Custodial History
Dr. Wilcox inherited the material from his wife, Dr. Nancy Willcox (née Nancy Posch), upon her death. Nancy Willcox was a graduate student of Dr. Kolin's in the late 1960s and inherited the items directly from Dr. Kolin.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9957101833606533
Biography
Alexander Kolin, Emeritus Professor of Biophysics, inventor of the electromagnetic flow meter and of isoelectric focusing, for which he was a strong candidate for the Nobel Prize, died April 21, 1997, at his home in Los Angeles at age 87, from cancer. Kolin was born in Odessa, Russia, on March 12, 1910. Neither of Kolin's parents had a scientific orientation, be he showed an early aptitude, doing experiments at home, from the age of six. Famine, revolution and subsequent difficult conditions in Russia induced the Kolin family to leave. They moved to Berlin, Germany, in 1922, where Kolin rapidly learned the German language, and with great sacrifices by his parents, received tutoring in basic subjects to make up for his previous lack of educational opportunity. The study of physics became his passion, and Kolin was inspired by the galaxy of famous physicists in Berlin, including Einstein, Planck, Schrodinger, Hertz, and Nernst. Kolin studied at the Technische Hochschule in Berlin, completing his undergraduate studies in physics, and accepting an opportunity to do his doctoral work under Gustav Hertz, studying plasmas. In 1933, with his work barely underway, Kolin and his parents were stunned by the news of the Reichstag fire, and decided to leave Germany. They moved to Czechoslovakia, where Kolin enrolled at the German University of Prague, and chose a new thesis topic, which he finished in the record time of fourteen months. Soon thereafter, young Kolin immigrated to the United States to seek work. Through a mutual friend, Kolin met Albert Einstein, whom he impressed sufficiently to merit several letters of recommendation, which eventually helped Kolin find a position at the Michael Reese Hospital in Chicago, Illinois, where he worked by day and did independent research at night. During this time, he invented and began to develop the electromagnetic flow meter, initially applying it to the measurement of blood flow in animals. For the past fifty years, electromagnetic flowmeters have been widely used in medicine and industry. Kolin held various research and teaching positions in Chicago and New York before becoming Assistant Professor at the University of Chicago in 1946. There, he wrote a textbook on physics, discovered the phenomenon of elctromagnetophoresis, and invented isoelectric focusing, a laboratory technique that is widely used in biomedical research. Kolin moved to UCLA in 1956, to do both teaching and research, and retired in 1977 as Emeritus Professor of Biophysics. During this period, he invented endless fluid belt electrophoresis; received the prestigious John Scott Medal for his invention of the blood flow meter; and received the Albert F. Sperry Medal for flowmeter developments. In 1977, he received the Alexander von Humboldt Award from the Federal Republic of Germany. In retirement, he continued to pursue scientific research until physically unable. His wife, Renee who passed away in 2003, survived Professor Kolin. [Adapted from an obituary written by Professor Kolin's former graduate student, Dr. Nancy Wilcox, April 21, 1997.]
Scope and Content
Collection consists of correspondence, paperwork on patented inventions, research and teaching materials, and numerous awards.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Correspondence
Patents
Research materials
Teaching materials
Awards.
Has materials in English and German.
Physicists -- United States -- Archives.; Kolin, Alexander, 1910-1997---Archives.
- Correspondence, Series 1.
  - Albert Einstein correspondence, 1934-1949 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    27 items including letters and envelopes. 14 letters contain Einstein's signature.
  - Arne Tiselius correspondence, 1955-1958 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Letters and envelopes from Nobel Prize winner Arne Tiselius to Alexander Kolin. 5 items.
  - Correspondence--Request University Patent reimbursement, 1972 November 28 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Letter from Alexander Kolin requesting reimbursement for the filing fee for the "Disclosure Document Program." Originally in folder titled "Commissioner of Patents Priority Letters."
  - Correspondece, 1932-1957 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    10 itmes including letters and envelopes.
  - Correspondence, 1958-1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    11 items including letters and envelopes. One n.d.
  - "Important Letters and Documents", 1957-1987 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Includes photocopies of letters, Kolins' marriage certificate, and original folder holding these items.
- Patents, Series 2.
  - Commissioner of Patents--Priority Letters--Disclosure Documents, 1972-1979 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Contains disclosure documents and handwritten explanations of inventions.
  - Commissioner of Patents-- U.S. Patent Offices Disclosures, 1972-1988 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Contains handwritten explanations of inventions and patent information.
  - "Invention Protection", 1979-1990 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    In original folder labeled "Invention Protection," are public vouchers for refunds from the Department of Commerce and Trademark Office for "Performance minus N". Disclosure Document Receipt Notices for "Alternating Field Iso Focusing," paper title, "Self-Contained Induction Rheoangiometer". Also includes a business card for Edward H. Loveman, and 3 envelopes, 2 of which are addressed to Alexander Kolin from Alexander Kolin and are unopened (and appear to be empty) and one which is from Alexander Kolin to the Commissioner of Patents and is opened.
  - Originals of UC Patents, 1972-1988 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Original patents from the United States, Canada, and Germany.
- Research Materials, Series 3.
  Notebooks and papers containing Kolin's research notes.
  - Academic document, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Kolin's academic document from the Oberrealschule in Berlin.
  - "Alexander Kolin, FDS 1958-64" notebook, 1958-1964 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    One notebook and 4 loose leaf sheets of notes inserted in front cover.
  - "Device for Measuring Fluid Flow", 1946 September 8 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Paper titled, "Device for Measuring Fluid Flow" signed by Alexander Kolin and Evelyn Rush the Notary Public of Cook County, Ill dated 1946 September 8. Postcard of "Domaine d'Esterel Ski Lodge Lac Masson Que'" dated 1946 September 8.
    General note
    Paper and postcard found together.
  - "Method for Determination of Speed of an Airplane, or Other Vehicle, with Respect to Ground", 1946 September 29 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    One sheet titled, "Method for Determination of Speed of an Airplane, or Other Vehicle, with Respect to Ground"
  - "Records of my Studies", 1929-1933 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    3 notebooks: "Belegbuch fur Studierende Technische Hochschule Berlin" 1929-1931, two items inserted; "Friedrich-Wilhelms Universitat zu Berlin Studienbuch" (1 of 2), 1929, one item inserted; "Friedrich-Wilhelms Universitat zu Berlin Studienbuch" (2 of 2), 1931-1933, one item inserted. Original envelope holding the notebooks is labelled by hand reading " Research of my Studies". 4 items.
  - Sterling Record Notebook, 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    One "Sterling Record" Notebook with Kolin's notes. Two loose leaf sheets of notes inserted in the middle of the notebook.
- Teaching Materials, Series 4.
  - 1967 Sigma Xi Lecture: "Michael Faraday: Glimpses of an Inspiring Life" (Box 2, Folder 7)
    1967 Sigma Xi Lecture titled, "Michael Faraday: Glimpses of an Inspiring Life"
    Note on first page reads: "File in vault."
  - Teaching Film: Electromagnetic Determination of Blood Flow and Vascular Diameter Changes Without Sugical Exposure of the Blood Vessels, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    1 item. Teaching Film: Electromagnetic Determination of Blood Flow and Vascular Diameter Changes Without Sugical Exposure of the Blood Vessels. Outline by Alexander Kolin, UCLA School of Medicine (Drs. R.N. MacAlpin and R.J. Steckel to be invited to participate in the narration and making of the final film.)
    Copyright Alexander Kolin, 1977
- Awards, Series 5.
  - Albert F. Sperry Award, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Framed Albert F. Sperry Award 1967 Presented for Distinguished Achievement to Alexander Kolin. The Intsrument Society of America.
  - Alexander von Humboldt-Stiftung Urkunde Award, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Framed Alexander von Humboldt-Stiftung Urkunde Prof. Dr. Alexander Kolin award.
  - The City of Philadelphia John Scott Medal and Premium Award, 1965 June 18 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Framed City of Philadelphia John Scott Medal and Premium Award to Alexander Kolin, Doctor Rerum Naturalium
  - Electrophoresis Society Founders Award 1981 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Professor Alexander Kolin Electrophoresis Society Founders Award 1981 For Outstanding Contributions to the Field. Plaque.
  - Instrument Society of America Albert F. Sperry Medal Award, 1967 September 12 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    "In recognition of his work of three decades in designing and developing magnetic flowmeters..." Medal
  - John Scott Medal to the Most Deserving (The), 1965 June 18 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Awarded by the City of Philadelphia the John Scott Medal to the Most Deserving Alexander Kolin Doctor Rerum Naturalium for the Invention of the Electro Magnetic Flow Meter. Medal.